Register of the Daniel Lerner collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Captured German Documents, 1944-1945 (Boxes 1-9)
  - SM-File
    - Fifteen extracts from letters written by German civilians and garrison soldiers, (#712), July-September 1944
    - Eleven extracts from letters written by a German woman, (#713), June-August 1944
    - Letter of Gefreiter Schmeer as given by postal and telegraph censorship, (#715), September 1944
    - Letter on conditions in Hamburg, (#716), October 1944
    - Report on Vatican politics, (#717), November 1944
    - Order to punish by death those who undermine the Wehrmacht's fighting spirit, (#718), November 1944
    - Diary of German soldier, (#720), January-August 1944
    - Memorandum on differences in punishment accorded officers and men, (#721), June 1944
    - Directives for behavior of German soldiers if taken prisoner, (#722), September 1944
    - List of NSDAP officials, (#725), October 1944
    - Seven extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#726), August 1944
    - Seventeen extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#727), August 1944
    - Extracts from four letters written by a German girl in labor camp, (#728), November 1944
    - Extracts from seven consecutive letters by a German woman, (#729), May-August 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#730), June-August 1944
    - List of names of German and Luxemburg people connected with the Luxemburg radio station during Nazi occupation, (#731), October 1944
    - Extracts from German soldiers' newspaper Der Skorpion, (#732), November 1944
    - Lecture by H. Kopperschmidt on sterilization, (#733), November 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German soldiers in Denmark, (#735), August 1944
    - Eight extracts from letters written by German soldiers and sailors in Denmark, (#736), August 1944
    - Diary of a German Feldwebel, (#737), August 1943-Ocotber 1944
    - Statement by Joachim Fernau on German victory, (#738), August 1944
    - Eight extracts from letters written by German soldier on the Western front, (#744), August-October 1944
    - Diary of a German soldier, (#745), February-June 1944
    - Memorandum on battle training of the Luftwaffe ground crews, (#746), March 1944
    - Order concerning punishment of political offenders in the Wehrmacht, (#747), August 1943
    - Reports on Allied leaflets, (#748), August 1943
    - Directives for the NSDAP in Trier in case of air raids, (#749), November 1944
    - Nineteen extracts from letters written by German soldiers and civilians, (#750), August-September 1944
    - Memorandum by Feldmarschall Keitel on corruption in German officer corps, (#751), February 1943
    - Monthly propaganda directives for local party groups, (#752), October 1944
    - Three extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Western front, (#754), September 1944
    - Memorandum on the relationship between the Wehrmacht and the Waffen-SS, (#755), July 1944
    - Memorandum: NSFOs should boost morale of German troops in Italy, (#760), July 1944
    - Order of the Day by Befehlshaber Nordostfrankreich, (#762), August 1944
    - Memorandum concerning increase of punishable offenses in a German division in Italy, (#763), August 1944
    - Decrees by Speer, (#767), August 1944
    - Memorandum regarding new weapon, (#770), August 1944
    - Eleven extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Western front, (#773), August-September 1944
    - Diary of Gefreiter Reinhard Karl Artur Scholz, (#776), August 1942-July 1944
    - Memorandum on spoiled and rusted ammunition, (#777), August 1944
    - Nine extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Western front, (#779), August-September 1944
    - Memorandum on Alsatian deserter, (#790), August 1944
    - Diary of Oberleutnant Hans Eggers, (#795), September 1944
    - Diary of Obergrenadier Paul Gerd Nowatzki, (#796), January-September 1944
    - Leaflets to citizens of Metz, (#876), November 1944
    - Two orders by Oberst Mueller, (#1034), April 1945 (Folder 8: 6)
    - Memorandum concerning punishment for breaking oath in the Wehrmacht, (#1518), October 1944
    - Memorandum concerning listening to London broadcasts, self-mutilation, treatment of Jehovah Witnesses, etc., (#1543), July 1944
    - Memorandum concerning discipline in the Wehrmacht, (#1548), October 1944
    - Two orders to fight to the last man, (#1587-1588), October 1944
    - Memorandum concerning punishment of deserters, (#1590), October 1944
    - Memorandum concerning looting by German troops on Reich territory, (#1593), September 1944
  - SR-File
    - Memorandum on new weapon, August 1944 (Folder 8: 7)
    - Nineteen extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Western front, (#773), August-September 1944
    - Forty-six extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#775), August-September 1944
    - Song "Edelweiss-Piraten," (#945), December 1944
    - Six extracts from letters written by German soldiers, (#1500), August-October 1944 (Folder 8: 8)
    - Duplicates (#1500-A)
    - Diary of Hitlerjugend official Hermann Boeroth, (#1501), December 1943-September 1944
    - Broadcast speech by Wilhelm Pieck, Freies Deutschland, (#1502), October 1944
    - Directives for German soldiers in Balkan countries, (#1503), November 1944
    - Eleven extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1504), October 1944
    - Directives for German troops: No looting in Germany, (#1505), September 1944
    - Diary of Unteroffizier Willy Hoischen, (#1504), January-September 1944
    - Memorandum concerning signs of disintegration in the Wehrmacht, (#1508), August 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Western front, (#1509), August 1944
    - Report on sabotage in France, (#1511), June 1944
    - Fourteen extracts from letters written by various Gestapo offices, (#1513), September 1944
    - Directives for German police concerning use of weapons against prisoners of war, (#1514), August 1942
    - Leaflet on necessity to defeat the Allies, (#1516), n.d.
    - Memorandum on low morale in soldiers' letters, (#1517), October 1944
    - Directives for NSDAP speakers, (#1519), February 1944
    - Directives on total mobilization, (#1528), September 1944
    - Report on low morale and shortages in the Wehrmacht, (#1532), October 1944
    - Soldiers' paper Zur Lage, No. 30/44 (#1533)
    - Directives about the Volkssturm, (#1534), September 1944
    - Rundstedt's memorandum on coming Allied attack,; and Dewitz's memorandum on German fighting planes, (#1535), October 1944 September 1944
    - Directives: No retreat from the West wall, (#1536), September 1944
    - Reports on morale and conduct of labor service men, (#1539), September 1944
    - Hitler's telegram to Oberst von Aulock urging him to hold St. Malo to the last bullet, (#1541), August 1944
    - Seventy extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1542), September-October 1944
    - Death sentence for cowardice and warning against looting, (#1544), September 1944
    - Report on clothing shortages in German Army, (#1547), October 1944
    - Report concerning smuggling of dutiable goods from Western occupied territories into Germany, (#1555), July 1944 (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - Memorandum on troops' qualities, (#1558), October 1944
    - Nine extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Western Front, (#1560), November 1944
    - Dr. Conti's considerations on how to influence raising the birth rate, (#1563), November 1944
    - Divisional court martial sentences for SS looters, etc., (#1564), November 1944
    - Battalion order to troops in Italy, (#1565), November 1944
    - Extracts from German civilians' letters, (#1566), November 1944
    - Drastic threats against soldiers joining the Nationalkomitee Freies Deutschland, on becoming POWs, (#1567), August 1944
    - Kesselring had to impose death penalty without court martial, as a last resort to stop excessive looting by German soldiers in Italy, (#1568), November 1944
    - Security Service "interested" in German employers fraternizing with foreign workers. Transfer of foreign men from border areas as Allied armies advance, (#1569), September 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1572), December 1944
    - Warnings against looting and desertions, (#1574), November 1944
    - Regimental commander promises enough fighter planes as soon as enough fuel can be produced, (#1575), September 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians inside Germany, (#1576), November 1944
    - Nazi paper's advertising methods, (#1577), December 1944
    - NSFO warning against Allies' cunning "whisper propaganda" (to troops defending Le Havre), (#1580), November 1944
    - As many men as possible to be released for front line duties; slacking to be checked and leisure to be cut down amongst men stationed at home, (#1581), November 1944
    - Eight extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1582), November 1944
    - Situation on the Western Front - Evacuation and removal of supplies from Aachen carried out in calm and orderly manner, (#1583), September 1944
    - Replacements for German unites must be "infiltrated" with the National Socialist spirit by Nazi commissars, (#1584), November 1944
    - NS-Commissar propaganda directive. Decrees of the Allies in occupied Germany "must be used to stir up hatred," (#1586), November 1944
    - Nazi press methods: Government's demands and instructions for anti-Jewish press campaign, (#1595), November 1944
    - Two men from Malm_ving in the German Army are anxious for the Allies to end the war quickly - these sympathies appear to be shared by Alsatians and Luxemburgers fighting on the Lithuanian front, (#1596), November 1944
    - Extracts from a letter written by a German sailor stationed on the Aegean coast at a "Seetransporthaupstelle," (#1597), November 1944
    - Extracts from diary of German officer Lt. Friedrich Jockschmann written in captivity, (#1598), December 1944
    - Extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Italian and Russian front, (#1599), December 1944
    - Pledge to hold Boulogne to the last man signed by officers of Gren. Rgt. 1039 and 3rd A.R. 164, (#1600), December 1944 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Extracts from "Mitteilungen f_pe," tactlessly worded (a) letters of condolence to relatives of fellow soldiers killed in action; (b) German authorities anxious: Wearing of trophies has been taken as indicating sympathy for the Russians; (c) "British stirring up hatred against officers," (#1606), December 1944
    - NCO observations from "Der politische Soldat," September 1944; importance of "so-called trivialities" regarding officers' conduct - Being "National' is not sufficient, we must also be called "social,'" (#1607), December 1944
    - NSFO directives, (#1608), December 1944
    - Extracts from speech on "Deutsche und europ3che Geistesfreiheit" by Alfred Rosenberg, delivered in Prague,; British and USA post-war aims - the Allies as "destructors of European culture," (#1609), 16 January 1944 December 1944
    - Twelve extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1610), December 1944
    - Names of prominent Nazi officials in "Kreis Diedenhofen" (Thionville), (#1611), December 1944
    - Admission of widespread distrust of German propaganda amongst German soldiers and civilians after Atlantic Wall fiasco, (#1612), December 1944
    - Sentences against members of Reich Labour Service (RAD), (#1613), December 1944
    - New form of self-mutilation - German soldiers damage or "lose" their dentures to get out of front-line fighting, (#1614), December 1944
    - Order by Commander of 10th Army on Army jurisdiction. Difficulties of maintaining discipline and order among units together in present emergency, (#1615), December 1944
    - Serious anti-German demonstrations by Labour (RAD) conscripts in Alsace and Lorraine (report on People's Court sentences), (#1616), December 1944
    - Twelve extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1617), December 1944
    - Report concerning German propaganda in the North-West, (#1618), April 1939
    - Directives: Fear of tanks must be overcome, (#1620), September 1944
    - Order on morale-building measures during fighting in Netherlands, (#1621), October 1944
    - Instructions: What should be reported to the troops, (#1623), October 1944
    - Directives: All unknown officers in German uniform giving unusual orders to be taken into custody, (#1624), October 1944
    - Directives for the treatment of the Volksdeutsche on Volksliste 3 (Polish), (#1624-A), October 1944
    - Memorandum on conduct of German troops in Italy, (#1625), October 1944
    - Eleven extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1626), October 1944
    - Notes of German soldiers on impact of Allied leaflets, (#1627), September 1944
    - Article by Reinecke in Der Politische Soldat, (#1628), October 1944
    - Instructions for the treatment of Volksdeutsche on Volksliste 3 (Polish), (#1629), October 1944
    - Memorandum on protection of decontamination units under the Geneva Convention, (#1630), October 1944
    - NSDAP directives how to combat current rumors, (#1631), November 1944
    - NSDAP directives regarding wine allowances for workers on fortification construction and also regarding lights or white marks on blocked roads, (#1632), November 1944
    - Memorandum on morale in the Wehrmacht, (#1633), October 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians and German soldiers stationed in Germany, (#1634), October-November 1944
    - Directives regarding the Volkssturm, (#1635), November 1944
    - Statement on marriage difficulties of a police inspector, (#1636), August 1944
    - Memorandum on confirmation of death sentences, (#1637), September 1944
    - Telegram from Himmler to all Gauleiters quoting Kesselring's message on the Volkssturm, (#1638), November 1944
    - Letter of a German soldier who never wanted to fight, (#1639), September 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Western front, (#1640), October-November 1944
    - Two letters by NSDAP members, (#1641), October-November 1944
    - Report on impact of Allied air raids on German industry and transport, (#1642), November 1944
    - NSFO leaflet to German troops on Allied atrocities: Read and learn to hate, (#1643), November 1944
    - Various documents concerning German concentration camps, (#1644), October-November 1944
    - Fifteen extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Western front, (#1645), November 1944
    - Extract from Die eiserne Faust, (#1646), November 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German soldiers on the Western front, (#1647), November 1944
    - Memorandum on five-day rest for fighting units, (#1648), December 1944
    - Memoranda and orders of 559th Volks.-Gren.-Division, (#1649), September-October 1944
    - Order by Berger for Nazi education of German soldiers, (#1685), August 1944 (Folder 9: 4)
    - Memorandum on restriction of private billets for troops, (#1686), November 1944
    - Propaganda directives, (#1687), October 1944
    - Directives for interrogation of Allied POWs, (#1688), October 1944
    - Propaganda leaflet for German troops, (#1689), January 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1690), December 1944
    - Extracts from Informationdienst der D.A.F., (#1691), May-June 1944
    - Directives for NSDAP members, (#1696), October 1944
    - Memorandum concerning participation in fortification works, (#1697), November 1944
    - Five extracts from letters written by German civilians and soldiers stationed in Germany, (#1700), December 1944-January 1945 (Folder 9: 5)
    - Leaflets to German troops, (#1702), March 1945
    - Memorandum on necessity to save grain and cattle, (#1703), December 1944
    - Twelve extracts from letters written by German civilians and soldiers stationed in Germany, (#1704), January 1945
    - Various documents on Interministerieller Luftkriegssch_Ausschuss (Ministerial Air Raid Damage Board), (#1705), 1944
    - Two letters concerning SA-Gruppe Oberrhein, (#1706), January 1945
    - Report concerning living conditions of fortification construction workers, (#1707), November 1944
    - Report by NSDAP central district office, (#1707-A), October 1944
    - Report on treatment of a German evacuated woman with seven children by a local NSDAP official, (#1708), October 1944
    - Ten extracts from letters written by German civilians and soldiers stationed in Germany, (#1709), January 1945
    - Report concerning food of fortification construction workers, (#1710), October 1944
    - Memorandum concerning plans for polygamy in Germany, (#1711), October 1944
    - Directives for better treatment of Eastern workers, (#1713), August 1944
    - Directives for NSFO of the Kriegsmarine (German Navy), (#1714), December 1944
    - Report by Bormann on corruption in Germany, (#1715), May 1944
    - Propaganda leaflets for troops, (#1716), November 1944
    - Order to hold position to the last drop of blood, (#1717), November 1944
    - Directives for the treatment of Russian POWs, (#1718), n.d.
    - Nine extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1719), January 1945
    - Directives on enrollment of NSDAP leaders in the army, (#1720), October 1944
    - Propaganda directives for NSFOs, (#1721), January 1945
    - Memorandum by Bormann that was approved by Himmler on enrollment of criminals and politically unreliable people in the Volkssturm, (#1722), November 1944
    - Eight extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1726), January 1945 (Folder 9: 6)
    - Report by Axmann on Hitlerjugend military training, (#1727), November 1944
    - Memorandum on children of German soldiers and non-German women, (#1765), November 1944 (Folder 9: 7)
    - Reports on mobilization of foreign and German labor in the period of 1942-1944, (#1766), September 1944
    - Seven extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1767), March 1945
    - Order concerning conscription of German soldiers who were exchanged from American and British POW camps, (#1768), October 1944
    - Eight extracts from letters written by German civilians, (#1770), March 1945
    - Hitler's order: Partisan war is to be waged against Allies, (#1771), April 1945
    - Otto Konrad Hellmuth's papers, (#1772), 1928-1945
    - Eleven letters by German civilians, (#1774), March 1945
    - Last proclamation by F. Sauckel, (#1775), April 1945
    - Himmler's directives for security of NSDAP officials, (#1776), n.d. (Folder 9: 8)
    - Himmler's memorandum on discipline in German army, (#1777), September 1944
    - Memorandum on bodies of dead inmates in concentration camps, (#1778), October 1944
    - Various documents relating to Reichstatthalter Sauckel's life style, (#1779), 1943-1944
    - Various documents from Sauckel's archives, (#1780), 1935-1936
    - Schoenhorn's order on deserters, (#1781), November 1944
    - Letters by General Hagler on German warfare, (#1782), July-August 1944
    - Bormann's last appeal to NSDAP leaders: Victory or death, (#1783), April 1945
    - Orders from the file of Reichsf_fice, (#1784), April 1939-1940
    - Report by a secret SD agent on morale in an army unit, (#1785), August 1940
    - Memorandum on treatment of foreign workers, (#1786), December 1942
    - Order and memorandum on 1938 election, (#1787)
    - Memorandum on search by Sonderkommando Rosenberg for libraries and papers of Jews and other NSDAP enemies, (#1789), May 1944
    - Göring's order to sentence officers and men to death and prisons, (#1790), January 1945
    - Memorandum by Backe concerning food supply, (#1791), February 1945
    - Memorandum concerning resistance movements among Allied POWs, (#1792), September 1944
    - Reports by the SD on morale of population, (#1793), 1938-1939
    - Speer's decree concerning requisition of raw materials from occupied territories, (#1796), January 1945
    - Letter on organization Osenberg - long-term plans for development of new weapons, (#1797), December 1944
    - Report on treatment of Russian and Polish workers in German camps, (#1798)
    - Letters to Generalmajor Theodor Scherer, (#1799), 1942-1944
    - Various materials concerning activities of Gauleiter P. Giesler, Munich, (#1801), June 1944-March 1945
    - Report concerning morale of American soldiers, (#1802), February 1945
- Censorship Reports, 1946-1947 (Boxes 10-14)
  Transcripts of and excerpts from letters and telephone conversations of German civilians processed by the United States Civil Censorship Submission, United States Forces European Theater, arranged chronologically
  - ., 1946
    - ., September (Folder 10: 1-6)
    - October (Folder 10: 7-8)
    - ., November (Folder 11: 1-5)
    - ., December (Folder 11: 6-7)
    - ., December (Box-folder 12: 1-3)
  - ., 1947
    - ., January (Folder 12: 4-6)
    - ., January (Box-folder 13: 1-3)
    - ., February (Folder 13: 4-7)
    - ., February (Box-folder 14: 1-3)
    - ., March (Folder 14: 4-8)
- Handbooks, Guides, and Manuals, 1942-1946 (Boxes 15-27)
  Arranged alphabetically by subject or issuing agent
  - Allied Expeditionary Forces. Supreme Headquarters.
    General note
    See HANDBOOKS, GUIDES, AND MANUALS/Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Forces
  - Foreign Office.
    See HANDBOOKS, GUIDES, AND MANUALS/ Ministry of Economic Warfare and Foreign Office
  - General Services Geographic Section (Great Britain).
    See HANDBOOKS, GUIDES, AND MANUALS/Netherlands - General Services Geographic Section
  - Inter-Service Topographical Department (Great Britain)
    - Aarhus (ï¿½rhus) (Folder 15: 1)
    - Augsburg (Folder 15: 2)
    - Berlin (Folder 15: 3)
    - Bremerhaven and Bremen
      - Ports (Folder 15: 4)
      - Towns (Folder 15: 5)
    - Copenhagen (Folder 15: 6)
    - Cuxhaven (Folder 15: 7)
    - Emden (Folder 15: 8)
    - Germany, Railways in. (Box 16)
      See HANDBOOKS, GUIDES, AND MANUALS/Inter-Service Topographical Department/ Railways in Germany
    - Hamburg (Folder 16: 1)
    - Kaiserlautern (Folder 16: 2)
    - Karlsruhe (Folder 16: 3)
    - Kiel (Folder 16: 4)
    - Mannheim-Ludwigshafen (Folder 16: 5)
    - Mulhouse (Folder 16: 6)
    - Munich (Folder 16: 7)
    - Nürnberg (Nuremberg) (Box-folder 17: 1)
    - Railways in Germany
      - North-West (Folder 17: 2)
      - South-West
        - General (Folder 17: 3)
        - Bridges (Folder 17: 4)
        - Tunnels (Folder 18: 1)
    - Regensburg (Folder 18: 2)
    - Saarbrücken (Folder 18: 3)
    - Strassbourg (Folder 18: 4)
    - Stuttgart (Folder 18: 5)
    - Ulm (Folder 18: 6)
    - Wilhemshaven (Folder 18: 7)
    - Würzburg (Folder 18: 8)
  - Italy (Box 19)
    - Agriculture.
      See HANDBOOKS, GUIDES, AND MANUALS/ Italy/Agriculture, Department of
    - Agriculture, Department of (Folder 19: 1)
    - Allied Commission - Manual on Materials (Folder 19: 2)
    - Allied Control Commission - Emergency Industrial Programme for the Rehabilitation of Italian Industry (Folder 19: 3)
    - Allied Military Government for Occupied Territories - Plans, Proclamations and Instructions (Folder 19: 4)
    - Allied Military Government, Liguria region - Guide to Operation Procedure for Regional Officers (Folder 19: 5)
    - Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System and the Federal Reserve Bank of New York (Folder 19: 6)
    - Federal Reserve Bank of New York.
      See HANDBOOKS, GUIDES, AND MANUALS/Italy/Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System
    - Industry, Rehabilitation of.
      See HANDBOOKS, GUIDES, AND MANUALS/Italy/Allied Control Commission
    - Labor.
      See HANDBOOKS, GUIDES, AND MANUALS/ Italy/Labor, Department of